<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Huma Saleem | Achal Neupane</title>
    <link>/achalneupane.github.io/authors/huma-saleem/</link>
      <atom:link href="/achalneupane.github.io/authors/huma-saleem/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Huma Saleem</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2019</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2019 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/achalneupane.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Huma Saleem</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/authors/huma-saleem/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roles of argonautes  and dicers on Sclerotinia sclerotiorum antiviral RNA silencing</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/neupane_etal_2019_frontiers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2019 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/neupane_etal_2019_frontiers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RNA silencing or RNA interference (RNAi) is an essential mechanism in animals, fungi, and plants that functions in gene regulation and defense against foreign nucleic acids. In fungi, RNA silencing has been shown to function primarily in defense against invasive nucleic acids. We previously determined that mycoviruses are triggers and targets of RNA silencing in Sclerotinia sclerotiorum. However, recent progresses in RNAi or dsRNA-based pest control requires more detailed characterization of the RNA silencing pathways in S. sclerotiorum to investigate the utility of dsRNA-based strategy for white mold control. This study elucidates the roles of argonaute enzymes, agl-2 and agl-4, in small RNA metabolism in S. sclerotiorum. Gene disruption mutants of agl-2 and agl-4 were compared for changes in phenotype, virulence, viral susceptibility, and small RNA profiles. The Δagl-2 mutant but not the Δagl-4 mutant had significantly slower growth and virulence prior to virus infection. Similarly, the Δagl-2 mutant but not the Δagl-4 mutant, showed greater debilitation under virus infection compared to uninfected strains. The responses were confirmed in complementation studies and revealed the antiviral role of agl-2. Gene disruption mutants of agl-2, agl-4, Dicer-like (dcl)-1, and dcl-2 did not change the stability of the most abundant endogenous small RNAs, which suggests the existence of alternative enzymes/pathways for small RNA biogenesis in S. sclerotiorum. Furthermore, in vitro synthesized dsRNA targeting agl-2 showed a significantly reduced average lesion diameter (P &amp;lt; 0.05) on canola leaves with agl-2 down-regulated compared to controls. This is the first report describing the effectiveness of RNA pesticides targeting S. sclerotiorum RNA silencing pathway for the control of the economically important pathogen.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Profiling the Classes of the RNA Editing in Virus-derived small RNAs in White Mold Sclerotinia sclerotiorum</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/asv_2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2019 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/asv_2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Profiling the classes of the RNA silencing, also known as RNA interference, is
an essential mechanism in plants, animals and fungi
that functions in gene regulation and defense against
foreign nucleic acids. In fungi, RNA silencing has
been shown to function primarily in defense against
invasive nucleic acids. RNA-silencing- deficient fungi
show increased susceptibility to virus infection. Little
is known about the classes of RNA editing in virus-
derived small RNA which will teach us the nature
of self-nonself recognition and ways to modulate
RNA modification to control fungal infections.
The present study dissects the RNA silencing pathway
in &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;sclerotiorum&lt;/em&gt; by disrupting its key silencing
genes using the split-marker recombination method
in order to probe the contributions of these genes,
specifically argonautes, to fungal virulence and viral
defense mechanisms. Following gene disruption,
mutants were studied for changes in phenotype,
pathogenicity, viral susceptibility, and small RNA
processing compared to the wild-type strain, DK3.
Among the argonaute mutants, the agl-2 mutant
had significantly slower growth and virulence prior
to and following virus infection. Additional analyses
indicated that the virus-infected wild-type strain
accumulated virus-derived small RNAS (vsiRNAs)
with distinct patterns of internal and terminal
nucleotide mismatches. Dicer 1 mutant produced
less vsiRNA compared to dicer 2 mutant and the wild
type strain, suggesting the two dicers are not in the
state of complete redundancy. This finding expands
our overall understanding of S. sclerotiorum and has
important implications for any current or future uses
of dsRNA and mycoviruses as disease control agents.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roles of Dicers and Argonautes on Sclerotinia sclerotiorum Antiviral Small RNA Processing</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/pag_2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jan 2019 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/pag_2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ProfilingRNA silencing, also known as RNA interference, is an essential mechanism in plants, animals and fungi that functions in gene regulation and defense against foreign nucleic acids. In fungi, RNA silencing has been shown to function primarily in defense against invasive nucleic acids. RNA-silencing- deficient fungi show increased susceptibility to virus infection. Plant pathogenic fungi also utilize RNA silencing to silence plant host immunity genes through the delivery of fungal small RNAs into plants. This cross-kingdom RNA silencing facilitates fungal infection of plants. Overall, these findings demonstrate the significant contributions of fungal RNA silencing pathways to fungal virulence and viral defense. This study dissects the RNA silencing pathway in S. sclerotiorum by disrupting its key silencing genes using the split-marker recombination method in order to probe the contributions of these genes, specifically argonautes, to fungal virulence and viral defense mechanisms. Following gene disruption, mutants were studied for changes in phenotype, pathogenicity, viral susceptibility, and small RNA processing compared to the wild-type strain, DK3. Among the argonaute mutants, the ∆agl-2 mutant had significantly slower growth and virulence prior to and following virus infection. Additional studies indicated that the virus-infected wild-type strain accumulated virus-derived smallRNAs(vsiRNAs) with distinct patterns of internal and terminal nucleotide mismatches. Additionally, dicer 1 mutant produced less vsiRNA compared to dicer 2 mutant and the wild type strain. These results together support that S. sclerotiorum has robust RNAsilencing mechanisms that function primarily in antiviral defense but also in endogenous gene regulation processes. This finding expands our overall understanding of S. sclerotiorum and has important implications for any current or future uses of mycoviruses as biological control agents, an emerging area of interest in fungal control research.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
