<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sarbottam Piya | Achal Neupane</title>
    <link>/achalneupane.github.io/authors/sarbottam-piya/</link>
      <atom:link href="/achalneupane.github.io/authors/sarbottam-piya/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Sarbottam Piya</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2019</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2014 00:00:00 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/achalneupane.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Sarbottam Piya</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/authors/sarbottam-piya/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genetic diversity and population structure of sickleweed(Falcaria vulgaris; Apiaceae) in the upper Midwest USA</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/piya_et_al_biological_invasions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2014 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/piya_et_al_biological_invasions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sickleweed (Falcaria vulgaris), an intro-duced species native to Europe and Asia, grows as anaggressive weed in some areas of the upper Midwest inthe United States. We are reporting genetic diversityand  population  structure  of  sickleweed  populationsusing microsatellite markers and nuclear and chloro-plast   DNA   sequences.   Populations   showed   highgenetic  differentiation  but  did  not  show  significantgeographic  structure,  suggesting  random  establish-ment of different genotypes at different sites was likelydue to human mediated multiple introductions. Threegenetic  clusters  revealed  by  microsatellite  data  andpresence of six chlorotypes supported our hypothesisof multiple introductions. Chloroplast DNA sequencedata  revealed  six  chlorotypes  nested  into  two  mainlineages   suggesting   at   least   two   introductions   ofsickleweed  in  the  upper  Midwest.  Some  individualsexhibited more than two alleles at several microsatel-lite  loci suggesting  occurrence  of polyploidy, whichcould be a post-introduction development to mitigatethe  inbreeding  effects.  High  genetic  variation  in  theintroduced range attributable to multiple introductionsand  polyploidy  may  be  inducing  the  evolution  ofinvasiveness  in  sickleweed.  Results  of  this  studyprovide valuable insights into the evolution of sickle-weed and baseline data for designing proper manage-ment practices for controlling sickleweed in the UnitedStates.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolutionary history of mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) genes in Lotus, Medicago, and Phaseolus</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/mapk_legume/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2013 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/mapk_legume/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mitogen-Activated Protein Kinase (MAPK) genes encode proteins that mediate various signaling pathways associated with biotic and abiotic stress responses in eukaryotes. The MAPK genes form a 3-tier signal transduction cascade between cellular stimuli and physiological responses. Recent identification of soybean MAPKs and availability of genome sequences from other legume species allowed us to identify their MAPK genes. The main objectives of this study were to identify MAPKs in 3 legume species, Lotus japonicus, Medicago truncatula, and Phaseolus vulgaris, and to assess their phylogenetic relationships. We used approaches in comparative genomics for MAPK gene identification and named the newly identified genes following Arabidopsis MAPK nomenclature model. We identified 19, 18, and 15 MAPKs and 7, 4, and 9 MAPKKs in the genome of Lotus japonicus, Medicago truncatula, and Phaseolus vulgaris, respectively. Within clade placement of MAPKs and MAPKKs in the 3 legume species were consistent with those in soybean and Arabidopsis. Among 5 clades of MAPKs, 4 founder clades were consistent to MAPKs of other plant species and orthologs of MAPK genes in the fifth clade-&amp;ldquo;Clade E&amp;rdquo; were consistent with those in soybean. Our results also indicated that some gene duplication events might have occurred prior to eudicot-monocot divergence. Highly diversified MAPKs in soybean relative to those in 3 other legume species are attributable to the polyploidization events in soybean. The identification of the MAPK genes in the legume species is important for the legume crop improvement; and evolutionary relationships and functional divergence of these gene members provide insights into plant genome evolution.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identification, Nomenclature, and Evolutionary Relationships of Mitogen-Activated Protein Kinase (MAPK) Genes in Soybean</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/mapk_soybean/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Sep 2013 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/mapk_soybean/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) genes in eukaryotes regulate various developmental and physiological processes
including those associated with biotic and abiotic stresses. Although MAPKs in some plant species including Arabidopsis have been
identified, they are yet to be identified in soybean. Major objectives of this study were to identify GmMAPKs, assess their evolutionary relationships, and analyze their functional divergence. We identified a total of 38 MAPKs, eleven MAPKKs, and 150 MAPKKKs in
soybean. Within the GmMAPK family, we also identified a new clade of six genes: four genes with TEY and two genes with TQY motifs
requiring further investigation into possible legume-specific functions. The results indicated the expansion of the GmMAPK families
attributable to the ancestral polyploidy events followed by chromosomal rearrangements. The GmMAPK and GmMAPKKK families
were substantially larger than those in other plant species. The duplicated GmMAPK members presented complex evolutionary relationships and functional divergence when compared to their counterparts in Arabidopsis. We also highlighted existing nomenclatural issues,
stressing the need for nomenclatural consistency. GmMAPK identification is vital to soybean crop improvement, and novel insights into
the evolutionary relationships will enhance our understanding about plant genome evolution.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identification of Mitogen Activated Protein Kinase Family Members in Soybean</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/bsa_neupane/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jul 2012 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/bsa_neupane/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mitogen Activated Protein Kinases (MAPKs) are serine/threonine specific kinases that are induced by various extracellular and intracellular stimuli, and are involved in signaling pathways in all eukaryotes. In plants, MAPKs are known to regulate various signal transduction pathways including those associated with biotic and abiotic stresses. The MAPK gene members belong to three functionally linked gene families called MAPKs, MAPKKs (MAPK Kinases) and MAPKKKs (MAPKK Kinases). Although, MAPKs of model plants such as &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Oryza&lt;/em&gt; have been identified and characterized, these genes in soybean (&lt;em&gt;Glycine max&lt;/em&gt;) are yet to be identified. In this study, we used approaches in comparative genomics and bioinformatics for the genome-wide identification of MAPKs, MAPKKs and MAPKKKs in soybean. &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/em&gt; reference sequences were used in protein BLAST to search the putative MAPKs of soybean from publicly available databases. In our in-silico analysis, the redundant sequences were removed to perform unbiased and rigorous phylogenetic analyses. We verified the presence of unique conserved domains and active sites in each putative MAPK gene member manually and by using Geneious and Pfam programs. From our three different confirmatory analyses, we identified 38 MAP Kinases, 11 MAPK Kinases and 115 MAPKK Kinases in soybean. &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/em&gt; nomenclature model was followed to assign numeric subscript to MAPK sequences grouped with &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/em&gt; sequences in phylogenetic tree. Lack of effective code of nomenclature lead us to a conundrum, which will be discussed in the meeting. Universal codes of gene nomenclature are crucial for understanding various signaling pathways. Therefore, an effective code of gene nomenclature is warranted. The results from this study will help us characterize soybean MAP Kinases paving avenue for the functional analyses of different cellular and physiological pathways in the order these genes function.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Population Genetics of *Falcaria vulgaris* (Sickleweed) in North America</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/piya_bsa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jul 2012 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/piya_bsa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction history and spread of Falcaria vulgaris Bernh. (Apiaceae) in the United States based on herbarium records</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/piya_sd_academy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Apr 2012 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/piya_sd_academy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Nomenclatural Conundrum: Applying Existing Nomenclature to the Identification of Soybean (*Glycine max*) MAP Kinase Genes</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/neupane_aspb/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Mar 2012 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/neupane_aspb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inferring Introduction History and Spread of Falcaria vulgaris Bernh.(Apiaceae) in the United States Based on Herbarium Records</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/piya_et_al_proceedings_sd/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2012 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/piya_et_al_proceedings_sd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Herbarium records were studied to infer the introduction history and spread of the exotic Eurasian sickleweed (Falcaria vulgaris Bernh.) in the United States. The spread of the plant was reconstructed using the location of early collections as the possible sites of primary introduction, and the location of subsequent collections as potential pathways along which this species spread. Herbarium records indicate that sickleweed was first introduced no later than 1922, and independent introduction of this plant took place in the East Coast and in the Midwest of the United States. The species has spread to 37 counties of 15 states of the United States. No recent sickleweed record has been reported for the last 17 years in the US except Iowa, Nebraska and South Dakota. The plant has been characterized as an aggressive weed by experts in the latter two states, where it is already well established and has infested the Fort Pierre National Grassland and Buffalo Gap National Grassland in South Dakota, and is reported from several sites along Nebraska roadsides. It is essential to verify the existence of sickleweed in the areas from where the herbarium specimens were previously collected to help identify the areas at risk. Control strategies need to be implemented and policy should be developed to establish the participation of public lands managers, transportation departments and private land-owners to control and manage this species before it becomes a more widespread invader.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
