<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Madhav P. Nepal | Achal Neupane</title>
    <link>/achalneupane.github.io/authors/madhav-p.-nepal/</link>
      <atom:link href="/achalneupane.github.io/authors/madhav-p.-nepal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Madhav P. Nepal</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2019</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 30 Jun 2018 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/achalneupane.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Madhav P. Nepal</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/authors/madhav-p.-nepal/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genome-Wide Identification of NBS-Encoding Resistance Genes in Sunflower (Helianthus annuus L.)</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/surendra_et_al_2018_july_genes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jun 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/surendra_et_al_2018_july_genes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nucleotide Binding Site-Leucine-Rich Repeat (NBS-LRR) genes encode disease resistance proteins involved in plants&amp;rsquo; defense against their pathogens. Although sunflower is affected by many diseases, only a few molecular details have been uncovered regarding pathogenesis and resistance mechanisms. Recent availability of sunflower whole genome sequences in publicly accessible databases allowed us to accomplish a genome-wide identification of Toll-interleukin-1 receptor-like Nucleotide-binding site Leucine-rich repeat (TNL), Coiled Coil (CC)-NBS-LRR (CNL), Resistance to powdery mildew 8 (RPW8)-NBS-LRR (RNL) and NBS-LRR (NL) protein encoding genes. Hidden Markov Model (HMM) profiling of 52,243 putative protein sequences from sunflower resulted in 352 NBS-encoding genes, among which 100 genes belong to CNL group including 64 genes with RX_CC like domain, 77 to TNL, 13 to RNL, and 162 belong to NL group. We also identified signal peptides and nuclear localization signals present in the identified genes and their homologs. We found that NBS genes were located on all chromosomes and formed 75 gene clusters, one-third of which were located on chromosome 13. Phylogenetic analyses between sunflower and Arabidopsis NBS genes revealed a clade-specific nesting pattern in CNLs, with RNLs nested in the CNL-A clade, and species-specific nesting pattern for TNLs. Surprisingly, we found a moderate bootstrap support (BS = 50%) for CNL-A clade being nested within TNL clade making both the CNL and TNL clades paraphyletic. Arabidopsis and sunflower showed 87 syntenic blocks with 1049 high synteny hits between chromosome 5 of Arabidopsis and chromosome 6 of sunflower. Expression data revealed functional divergence of the NBS genes with basal level tissue-specific expression. This study represents the first genome-wide identification of NBS genes in sunflower paving avenues for functional characterization and potential crop improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genetic diversity and population structure of sickleweed(Falcaria vulgaris; Apiaceae) in the upper Midwest USA</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/piya_et_al_biological_invasions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2014 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/piya_et_al_biological_invasions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sickleweed (Falcaria vulgaris), an intro-duced species native to Europe and Asia, grows as anaggressive weed in some areas of the upper Midwest inthe United States. We are reporting genetic diversityand  population  structure  of  sickleweed  populationsusing microsatellite markers and nuclear and chloro-plast   DNA   sequences.   Populations   showed   highgenetic  differentiation  but  did  not  show  significantgeographic  structure,  suggesting  random  establish-ment of different genotypes at different sites was likelydue to human mediated multiple introductions. Threegenetic  clusters  revealed  by  microsatellite  data  andpresence of six chlorotypes supported our hypothesisof multiple introductions. Chloroplast DNA sequencedata  revealed  six  chlorotypes  nested  into  two  mainlineages   suggesting   at   least   two   introductions   ofsickleweed  in  the  upper  Midwest.  Some  individualsexhibited more than two alleles at several microsatel-lite  loci suggesting  occurrence  of polyploidy, whichcould be a post-introduction development to mitigatethe  inbreeding  effects.  High  genetic  variation  in  theintroduced range attributable to multiple introductionsand  polyploidy  may  be  inducing  the  evolution  ofinvasiveness  in  sickleweed.  Results  of  this  studyprovide valuable insights into the evolution of sickle-weed and baseline data for designing proper manage-ment practices for controlling sickleweed in the UnitedStates.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identification of Mitogen Activated Protein Kinase Family Members in Soybean</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/bsa_neupane/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jul 2012 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/bsa_neupane/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Location: Ohio, USA&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Event: Botanical Society of America Conference, 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mitogen Activated Protein Kinases (MAPKs) are serine/threonine specific kinases that are induced by various extracellular and intracellular stimuli, and are involved in signaling pathways in all eukaryotes. In plants, MAPKs are known to regulate various signal transduction pathways including those associated with biotic and abiotic stresses. The MAPK gene members belong to three functionally linked gene families called MAPKs, MAPKKs (MAPK Kinases) and MAPKKKs (MAPKK Kinases). Although, MAPKs of model plants such as &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Oryza&lt;/em&gt; have been identified and characterized, these genes in soybean (&lt;em&gt;Glycine max&lt;/em&gt;) are yet to be identified. In this study, we used approaches in comparative genomics and bioinformatics for the genome-wide identification of MAPKs, MAPKKs and MAPKKKs in soybean. &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/em&gt; reference sequences were used in protein BLAST to search the putative MAPKs of soybean from publicly available databases. In our in-silico analysis, the redundant sequences were removed to perform unbiased and rigorous phylogenetic analyses. We verified the presence of unique conserved domains and active sites in each putative MAPK gene member manually and by using Geneious and Pfam programs. From our three different confirmatory analyses, we identified 38 MAP Kinases, 11 MAPK Kinases and 115 MAPKK Kinases in soybean. &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/em&gt; nomenclature model was followed to assign numeric subscript to MAPK sequences grouped with &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/em&gt; sequences in phylogenetic tree. Lack of effective code of nomenclature lead us to a conundrum, which will be discussed in the meeting. Universal codes of gene nomenclature are crucial for understanding various signaling pathways. Therefore, an effective code of gene nomenclature is warranted. The results from this study will help us characterize soybean MAP Kinases paving avenue for the functional analyses of different cellular and physiological pathways in the order these genes function.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inferring Introduction History and Spread of Falcaria vulgaris Bernh.(Apiaceae) in the United States Based on Herbarium Records</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/piya_et_al_proceedings_sd/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2012 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/piya_et_al_proceedings_sd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Herbarium records were studied to infer the introduction history and spread of the exotic Eurasian sickleweed (Falcaria vulgaris Bernh.) in the United States. The spread of the plant was reconstructed using the location of early collections as the possible sites of primary introduction, and the location of subsequent collections as potential pathways along which this species spread. Herbarium records indicate that sickleweed was first introduced no later than 1922, and independent introduction of this plant took place in the East Coast and in the Midwest of the United States. The species has spread to 37 counties of 15 states of the United States. No recent sickleweed record has been reported for the last 17 years in the US except Iowa, Nebraska and South Dakota. The plant has been characterized as an aggressive weed by experts in the latter two states, where it is already well established and has infested the Fort Pierre National Grassland and Buffalo Gap National Grassland in South Dakota, and is reported from several sites along Nebraska roadsides. It is essential to verify the existence of sickleweed in the areas from where the herbarium specimens were previously collected to help identify the areas at risk. Control strategies need to be implemented and policy should be developed to establish the participation of public lands managers, transportation departments and private land-owners to control and manage this species before it becomes a more widespread invader.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
