<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Senthil Subramanian | Achal Neupane</title>
    <link>/achalneupane.github.io/authors/senthil-subramanian/</link>
      <atom:link href="/achalneupane.github.io/authors/senthil-subramanian/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Senthil Subramanian</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2019</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 Sep 2013 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/achalneupane.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Senthil Subramanian</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/authors/senthil-subramanian/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identification, Nomenclature, and Evolutionary Relationships of Mitogen-Activated Protein Kinase (MAPK) Genes in Soybean</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/mapk_soybean/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Sep 2013 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/mapk_soybean/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) genes in eukaryotes regulate various developmental and physiological processes
including those associated with biotic and abiotic stresses. Although MAPKs in some plant species including Arabidopsis have been
identified, they are yet to be identified in soybean. Major objectives of this study were to identify GmMAPKs, assess their evolutionary relationships, and analyze their functional divergence. We identified a total of 38 MAPKs, eleven MAPKKs, and 150 MAPKKKs in
soybean. Within the GmMAPK family, we also identified a new clade of six genes: four genes with TEY and two genes with TQY motifs
requiring further investigation into possible legume-specific functions. The results indicated the expansion of the GmMAPK families
attributable to the ancestral polyploidy events followed by chromosomal rearrangements. The GmMAPK and GmMAPKKK families
were substantially larger than those in other plant species. The duplicated GmMAPK members presented complex evolutionary relationships and functional divergence when compared to their counterparts in Arabidopsis. We also highlighted existing nomenclatural issues,
stressing the need for nomenclatural consistency. GmMAPK identification is vital to soybean crop improvement, and novel insights into
the evolutionary relationships will enhance our understanding about plant genome evolution.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identification of Mitogen Activated Protein Kinase Family Members in Soybean</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/bsa_neupane/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jul 2012 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/bsa_neupane/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mitogen Activated Protein Kinases (MAPKs) are serine/threonine specific kinases that are induced by various extracellular and intracellular stimuli, and are involved in signaling pathways in all eukaryotes. In plants, MAPKs are known to regulate various signal transduction pathways including those associated with biotic and abiotic stresses. The MAPK gene members belong to three functionally linked gene families called MAPKs, MAPKKs (MAPK Kinases) and MAPKKKs (MAPKK Kinases). Although, MAPKs of model plants such as &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Oryza&lt;/em&gt; have been identified and characterized, these genes in soybean (&lt;em&gt;Glycine max&lt;/em&gt;) are yet to be identified. In this study, we used approaches in comparative genomics and bioinformatics for the genome-wide identification of MAPKs, MAPKKs and MAPKKKs in soybean. &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/em&gt; reference sequences were used in protein BLAST to search the putative MAPKs of soybean from publicly available databases. In our in-silico analysis, the redundant sequences were removed to perform unbiased and rigorous phylogenetic analyses. We verified the presence of unique conserved domains and active sites in each putative MAPK gene member manually and by using Geneious and Pfam programs. From our three different confirmatory analyses, we identified 38 MAP Kinases, 11 MAPK Kinases and 115 MAPKK Kinases in soybean. &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/em&gt; nomenclature model was followed to assign numeric subscript to MAPK sequences grouped with &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/em&gt; sequences in phylogenetic tree. Lack of effective code of nomenclature lead us to a conundrum, which will be discussed in the meeting. Universal codes of gene nomenclature are crucial for understanding various signaling pathways. Therefore, an effective code of gene nomenclature is warranted. The results from this study will help us characterize soybean MAP Kinases paving avenue for the functional analyses of different cellular and physiological pathways in the order these genes function.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Nomenclatural Conundrum: Applying Existing Nomenclature to the Identification of Soybean (*Glycine max*) MAP Kinase Genes</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/neupane_aspb/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Mar 2012 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/neupane_aspb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
