<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rachel Burow | Achal Neupane</title>
    <link>achalneupane.github.io/authors/rachel-burow/</link>
      <atom:link href="achalneupane.github.io/authors/rachel-burow/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Rachel Burow</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2019</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>achalneupane.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Rachel Burow</title>
      <link>achalneupane.github.io/authors/rachel-burow/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>MEK inhibitor resistance in acute myeloid leukaemia</title>
      <link>achalneupane.github.io/talk/mek_brisbane_2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>achalneupane.github.io/talk/mek_brisbane_2016/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Location: Peppers Noosa, Australia&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Event: New Direction in Leukaemia Research, 2016&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mutations of the RAS family of genes are frequent events in AML, occurring in 10% of children and 10-20% of adults.
NRASmutations promote proliferation through activation of the Ras/Raf/MEK/ERK signalling pathway. Several MEK
inhibitors have shown promising pre-clinical activity in AML, with a number of compounds currently in adult phase I/II
clinical trials, including AZD6244, GSK1120212 and AS703026. Given not all patients respond to MEK inhibitor
treatment we undertook a comprehensive preclinical evaluation of MEK inhibitors in AML and developed a clinically
relevant model of resistance.
The in vitroefficacy of 7 MEK inhibitors was determined using a diverse panel of 6 paediatric and 5 adult AML cell lines
(Table 1). All AML cell lines were sensitive to at least one MEK inhibitor with the exception of the Down syndrome
associated AML line, CMK, and the adult erythroblastic line, HEL, that showed overt resistance (IC50 &amp;gt;20μM) to MEK
inhibition (Table 1). In sensitive cell lines, the reduced proliferation was associated with apoptosis, as assessed by
Annexin V+ staining. To confirm mechanism of action, inhibition of MEK phosphorylation as well as the downstream
kinase, pERK, were assessed by immunoblotting. The level of basal MEK activation was variable across the cell line
panel and pMEK was increased upon exposure to active MEK inhibitors. In contrast, levels of pERK were reduced
suggesting that MEK inhibitors may disrupt the interaction of MEK with its downstream transducers rather than a direct
inhibition of MEK phosphorylation.
Molecular and clinical resistance to kinase inhibitors is well described for targets such as FLT3 and BCR-ABL1. Since
clinical responses to MEK inhibitors have been variable, we investigated the potential mechanisms of resistance to
MEK inhibitors in vitro. Long-term culture of THP-1 cells (MLL-rearranged, NRASmutated) with AZD6244 and
AS703026, resulted in high-level resistance. Importantly, cells displayed cross-resistance not only to these two
compounds but also a third MEK inhibitor, GSK1120212 (Table 2). Resistance was associated with reduced basal
pMEK expression. In order to establish the mechanism of resistance we performed comprehensive mutation and gene
expression analyses utilising whole-exome sequencing and RNAseq respectively. These data revealed a spectrum of
acquired molecular aberrations common to both resistant cell lines compared to the parental THP1 cells. Together,
these data indicate that whilst MEK inhibition is a promising strategy to treat AML, resistance to one MEK inhibitor may
lead to cross-resistance to other compounds targeting MEK.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
