<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jack L. Butler | Achal Neupane</title>
    <link>/achalneupane.github.io/authors/jack-l.-butler/</link>
      <atom:link href="/achalneupane.github.io/authors/jack-l.-butler/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Jack L. Butler</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2019</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2014 00:00:00 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/achalneupane.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Jack L. Butler</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/authors/jack-l.-butler/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genetic diversity and population structure of sickleweed(Falcaria vulgaris; Apiaceae) in the upper Midwest USA</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/piya_et_al_biological_invasions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2014 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/piya_et_al_biological_invasions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sickleweed (Falcaria vulgaris), an intro-duced species native to Europe and Asia, grows as anaggressive weed in some areas of the upper Midwest inthe United States. We are reporting genetic diversityand  population  structure  of  sickleweed  populationsusing microsatellite markers and nuclear and chloro-plast   DNA   sequences.   Populations   showed   highgenetic  differentiation  but  did  not  show  significantgeographic  structure,  suggesting  random  establish-ment of different genotypes at different sites was likelydue to human mediated multiple introductions. Threegenetic  clusters  revealed  by  microsatellite  data  andpresence of six chlorotypes supported our hypothesisof multiple introductions. Chloroplast DNA sequencedata  revealed  six  chlorotypes  nested  into  two  mainlineages   suggesting   at   least   two   introductions   ofsickleweed  in  the  upper  Midwest.  Some  individualsexhibited more than two alleles at several microsatel-lite  loci suggesting  occurrence  of polyploidy, whichcould be a post-introduction development to mitigatethe  inbreeding  effects.  High  genetic  variation  in  theintroduced range attributable to multiple introductionsand  polyploidy  may  be  inducing  the  evolution  ofinvasiveness  in  sickleweed.  Results  of  this  studyprovide valuable insights into the evolution of sickle-weed and baseline data for designing proper manage-ment practices for controlling sickleweed in the UnitedStates.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inferring Introduction History and Spread of Falcaria vulgaris Bernh.(Apiaceae) in the United States Based on Herbarium Records</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/piya_et_al_proceedings_sd/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2012 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/piya_et_al_proceedings_sd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Herbarium records were studied to infer the introduction history and spread of the exotic Eurasian sickleweed (Falcaria vulgaris Bernh.) in the United States. The spread of the plant was reconstructed using the location of early collections as the possible sites of primary introduction, and the location of subsequent collections as potential pathways along which this species spread. Herbarium records indicate that sickleweed was first introduced no later than 1922, and independent introduction of this plant took place in the East Coast and in the Midwest of the United States. The species has spread to 37 counties of 15 states of the United States. No recent sickleweed record has been reported for the last 17 years in the US except Iowa, Nebraska and South Dakota. The plant has been characterized as an aggressive weed by experts in the latter two states, where it is already well established and has infested the Fort Pierre National Grassland and Buffalo Gap National Grassland in South Dakota, and is reported from several sites along Nebraska roadsides. It is essential to verify the existence of sickleweed in the areas from where the herbarium specimens were previously collected to help identify the areas at risk. Control strategies need to be implemented and policy should be developed to establish the participation of public lands managers, transportation departments and private land-owners to control and manage this species before it becomes a more widespread invader.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
