<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>**Achal Neupane** | Achal Neupane</title>
    <link>/achalneupane.github.io/authors/achal-neupane/</link>
      <atom:link href="/achalneupane.github.io/authors/achal-neupane/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>**Achal Neupane**</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2019</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2019 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/achalneupane.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>**Achal Neupane**</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/authors/achal-neupane/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roles of argonautes  and dicers on Sclerotinia sclerotiorum antiviral RNA silencing</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/neupane_etal_2019_frontiers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2019 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/neupane_etal_2019_frontiers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RNA silencing or RNA interference (RNAi) is an essential mechanism in animals, fungi, and plants that functions in gene regulation and defense against foreign nucleic acids. In fungi, RNA silencing has been shown to function primarily in defense against invasive nucleic acids. We previously determined that mycoviruses are triggers and targets of RNA silencing in Sclerotinia sclerotiorum. However, recent progresses in RNAi or dsRNA-based pest control requires more detailed characterization of the RNA silencing pathways in S. sclerotiorum to investigate the utility of dsRNA-based strategy for white mold control. This study elucidates the roles of argonaute enzymes, agl-2 and agl-4, in small RNA metabolism in S. sclerotiorum. Gene disruption mutants of agl-2 and agl-4 were compared for changes in phenotype, virulence, viral susceptibility, and small RNA profiles. The Δagl-2 mutant but not the Δagl-4 mutant had significantly slower growth and virulence prior to virus infection. Similarly, the Δagl-2 mutant but not the Δagl-4 mutant, showed greater debilitation under virus infection compared to uninfected strains. The responses were confirmed in complementation studies and revealed the antiviral role of agl-2. Gene disruption mutants of agl-2, agl-4, Dicer-like (dcl)-1, and dcl-2 did not change the stability of the most abundant endogenous small RNAs, which suggests the existence of alternative enzymes/pathways for small RNA biogenesis in S. sclerotiorum. Furthermore, in vitro synthesized dsRNA targeting agl-2 showed a significantly reduced average lesion diameter (P &amp;lt; 0.05) on canola leaves with agl-2 down-regulated compared to controls. This is the first report describing the effectiveness of RNA pesticides targeting S. sclerotiorum RNA silencing pathway for the control of the economically important pathogen.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Profiling the Classes of the RNA Editing in Virus-derived small RNAs in White Mold Sclerotinia sclerotiorum</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/asv_2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2019 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/asv_2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Location: Minneapolis, USA&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Event: American Society for Virology&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Profiling the classes of the RNA silencing, also known as RNA interference, is
an essential mechanism in plants, animals and fungi
that functions in gene regulation and defense against
foreign nucleic acids. In fungi, RNA silencing has
been shown to function primarily in defense against
invasive nucleic acids. RNA-silencing- deficient fungi
show increased susceptibility to virus infection. Little
is known about the classes of RNA editing in virus-
derived small RNA which will teach us the nature
of self-nonself recognition and ways to modulate
RNA modification to control fungal infections.
The present study dissects the RNA silencing pathway
in &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;sclerotiorum&lt;/em&gt; by disrupting its key silencing
genes using the split-marker recombination method
in order to probe the contributions of these genes,
specifically argonautes, to fungal virulence and viral
defense mechanisms. Following gene disruption,
mutants were studied for changes in phenotype,
pathogenicity, viral susceptibility, and small RNA
processing compared to the wild-type strain, DK3.
Among the argonaute mutants, the agl-2 mutant
had significantly slower growth and virulence prior
to and following virus infection. Additional analyses
indicated that the virus-infected wild-type strain
accumulated virus-derived small RNAS (vsiRNAs)
with distinct patterns of internal and terminal
nucleotide mismatches. Dicer 1 mutant produced
less vsiRNA compared to dicer 2 mutant and the wild
type strain, suggesting the two dicers are not in the
state of complete redundancy. This finding expands
our overall understanding of S. sclerotiorum and has
important implications for any current or future uses
of dsRNA and mycoviruses as disease control agents.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identification and Characterization of Mitogen-Activated Protein Kinase (MAPK) Genes in Sunflower (Helianthus annuus L.)</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/surendra_et_al_2019_plants/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jan 2019 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/surendra_et_al_2019_plants/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mitogen-Activated Protein Kinase (MAPK) genes encode proteins that regulate biotic and abiotic stresses in plants through signaling cascades comprised of three major subfamilies: MAP Kinase (MPK), MAPK Kinase (MKK), and MAPKK Kinase (MKKK). The main objectives of this research were to conduct genome-wide identification of MAPK genes in Helianthus annuus and examine functional divergence of these genes in relation to those in nine other plant species (Amborella trichopoda, Aquilegia coerulea, Arabidopsis thaliana, Daucus carota, Glycine max, Oryza sativa, Solanum lycopersicum, Sphagnum fallax, and Vitis vinifera), representing diverse taxonomic groups of the Plant Kingdom. A Hidden Markov Model (HMM) profile of the MAPK genes utilized reference sequences from A. thaliana and G. max, yielding a total of 96 MPKs and 37 MKKs in the genomes of A. trichopoda, A. coerulea, C. reinhardtii, D. carota, H. annuus, S. lycopersicum, and S. fallax. Among them, 28 MPKs and eight MKKs were confirmed in H. annuus. Phylogenetic analyses revealed four clades within each subfamily. Transcriptomic analyses showed that at least 19 HaMPK and seven HaMKK genes were induced in response to salicylic acid (SA), sodium chloride (NaCl), and polyethylene glycol (Peg) in leaves and roots. Of the seven published sunflower microRNAs, five microRNA families are involved in targeting eight MPKs. Additionally, we discussed the need for using MAP Kinase nomenclature guidelines across plant species. Our identification and characterization of MAP Kinase genes would have implications in sunflower crop improvement, and in advancing our knowledge of the diversity and evolution of MAPK genes in the Plant Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roles of Dicers and Argonautes on Sclerotinia sclerotiorum Antiviral Small RNA Processing</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/pag_2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jan 2019 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/pag_2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Location: San Diego, USA&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Event: Plant and Animal Genome Conference, XXVII&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ProfilingRNA silencing, also known as RNA interference, is an essential mechanism in plants, animals and fungi that functions in gene regulation and defense against foreign nucleic acids. In fungi, RNA silencing has been shown to function primarily in defense against invasive nucleic acids. RNA-silencing- deficient fungi show increased susceptibility to virus infection. Plant pathogenic fungi also utilize RNA silencing to silence plant host immunity genes through the delivery of fungal small RNAs into plants. This cross-kingdom RNA silencing facilitates fungal infection of plants. Overall, these findings demonstrate the significant contributions of fungal RNA silencing pathways to fungal virulence and viral defense. This study dissects the RNA silencing pathway in S. sclerotiorum by disrupting its key silencing genes using the split-marker recombination method in order to probe the contributions of these genes, specifically argonautes, to fungal virulence and viral defense mechanisms. Following gene disruption, mutants were studied for changes in phenotype, pathogenicity, viral susceptibility, and small RNA processing compared to the wild-type strain, DK3. Among the argonaute mutants, the ∆agl-2 mutant had significantly slower growth and virulence prior to and following virus infection. Additional studies indicated that the virus-infected wild-type strain accumulated virus-derived smallRNAs(vsiRNAs) with distinct patterns of internal and terminal nucleotide mismatches. Additionally, dicer 1 mutant produced less vsiRNA compared to dicer 2 mutant and the wild type strain. These results together support that S. sclerotiorum has robust RNAsilencing mechanisms that function primarily in antiviral defense but also in endogenous gene regulation processes. This finding expands our overall understanding of S. sclerotiorum and has important implications for any current or future uses of mycoviruses as biological control agents, an emerging area of interest in fungal control research.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Metatranscriptomic analysis and in silico approach identified mycoviruses in the arbuscular mycorrhizal fungus Rhizophagus spp.</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/neupane_etal_viruses_2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2018 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/neupane_etal_viruses_2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi (AMF), including Rhizophagus spp., can play important roles in nutrient cycling of the rhizosphere. However, the effect of virus infection on AMF’s role in nutrient cycling cannot be determined without first knowing the diversity of the mycoviruses in AMF. Therefore, in this study, we sequenced the R. irregularis isolate-09 due to its previously demonstrated high efficiency in increasing the N/P uptake of the plant. We identified one novel mitovirus contig of 3685 bp, further confirmed by reverse transcription-PCR. Also, publicly available Rhizophagus spp. RNA-Seq data were analyzed to recover five partial virus sequences from family Narnaviridae, among which four were from R. diaphanum MUCL-43196 and one was from R. irregularis strain-C2 that was similar to members of the Mitovirus genus. These contigs coded genomes larger than the regular mitoviruses infecting pathogenic fungi and can be translated by either a mitochondrial translation code or a cytoplasmic translation code, which was also reported in previously found mitoviruses infecting mycorrhizae. The five newly identified virus sequences are comprised of functionally conserved RdRp motifs and formed two separate subclades with mitoviruses infecting Gigaspora margarita and Rhizophagus clarus, further supporting virus-host co-evolution theory. This study expands our understanding of virus diversity. Even though AMF is notably hard to investigate due to its biotrophic nature, this study demonstrates the utility of whole root metatranscriptome.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transcriptional and small RNA responses of the white mold fungus Sclerotinia sclerotiorum to infection by a virulence-attenuating hypovirus</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/marzano_etal_viruses_2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Dec 2018 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/marzano_etal_viruses_2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mycoviruses belonging to the family Hypoviridae cause persistent infection of many different host fungi. We previously determined that the white mold fungus, Sclerotinia sclerotiorum, infected with Sclerotinia sclerotiorum hypovirus 2-L (SsHV2-L) exhibits reduced virulence, delayed/reduced sclerotial formation, and enhanced production of aerial mycelia. To gain better insight into the cellular basis for these changes, we characterized changes in mRNA and small RNA (sRNA) accumulation in S. sclerotiorum to infection by SsHV2-L. A total of 958 mRNAs and 835 sRNA-producing loci were altered after infection by SsHV2-L, among which &amp;gt;100 mRNAs were predicted to encode proteins involved in the metabolism and trafficking of carbohydrates and lipids. Both S. sclerotiorum endogenous and virus-derived sRNAs were predominantly 22 nt in length suggesting one dicer-like enzyme cleaves both. Novel classes of endogenous small RNAs were predicted, including phasiRNAs and tRNA-derived small RNAs. Moreover, S. sclerotiorum phasiRNAs, which were derived from noncoding RNAs and have the potential to regulate mRNA abundance in trans, showed differential accumulation due to virus infection. tRNA fragments did not accumulate differentially after hypovirus infection. Hence, in-depth analysis showed that infection of S. sclerotiorum by a hypovirulence-inducing hypovirus produced selective, large-scale reprogramming of mRNA and sRNA production.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genome-Wide Identification of NBS-Encoding Resistance Genes in Sunflower (Helianthus annuus L.)</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/surendra_et_al_2018_july_genes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jun 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/surendra_et_al_2018_july_genes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nucleotide Binding Site-Leucine-Rich Repeat (NBS-LRR) genes encode disease resistance proteins involved in plants&amp;rsquo; defense against their pathogens. Although sunflower is affected by many diseases, only a few molecular details have been uncovered regarding pathogenesis and resistance mechanisms. Recent availability of sunflower whole genome sequences in publicly accessible databases allowed us to accomplish a genome-wide identification of Toll-interleukin-1 receptor-like Nucleotide-binding site Leucine-rich repeat (TNL), Coiled Coil (CC)-NBS-LRR (CNL), Resistance to powdery mildew 8 (RPW8)-NBS-LRR (RNL) and NBS-LRR (NL) protein encoding genes. Hidden Markov Model (HMM) profiling of 52,243 putative protein sequences from sunflower resulted in 352 NBS-encoding genes, among which 100 genes belong to CNL group including 64 genes with RX_CC like domain, 77 to TNL, 13 to RNL, and 162 belong to NL group. We also identified signal peptides and nuclear localization signals present in the identified genes and their homologs. We found that NBS genes were located on all chromosomes and formed 75 gene clusters, one-third of which were located on chromosome 13. Phylogenetic analyses between sunflower and Arabidopsis NBS genes revealed a clade-specific nesting pattern in CNLs, with RNLs nested in the CNL-A clade, and species-specific nesting pattern for TNLs. Surprisingly, we found a moderate bootstrap support (BS = 50%) for CNL-A clade being nested within TNL clade making both the CNL and TNL clades paraphyletic. Arabidopsis and sunflower showed 87 syntenic blocks with 1049 high synteny hits between chromosome 5 of Arabidopsis and chromosome 6 of sunflower. Expression data revealed functional divergence of the NBS genes with basal level tissue-specific expression. This study represents the first genome-wide identification of NBS genes in sunflower paving avenues for functional characterization and potential crop improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mycoviruses as Triggers and Targets of RNA Silencing in White Mold Fungus Sclerotinia sclerotiorum</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/mochama_et_al/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Apr 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/mochama_et_al/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This study aimed to demonstrate the existence of antiviral RNA silencing mechanisms in Sclerotinia sclerotiorum by infecting wild-type and RNA-silencing-deficient strains of the fungus with an RNA virus and a DNA virus. Key silencing-related genes were disrupted to dissect the RNA silencing pathway. Specifically, dicer genes (dcl-1, dcl-2, and both dcl-1/dcl-2) were displaced by selective marker(s). Disruption mutants were then compared for changes in phenotype, virulence, and susceptibility to virus infections. Wild-type and mutant strains were transfected with a single-stranded RNA virus, SsHV2-L, and copies of a single-stranded DNA mycovirus, SsHADV-1, as a synthetic virus constructed in this study. Disruption of dcl-1 or dcl-2 resulted in no changes in phenotype compared to wild-type S. sclerotiorum; however, the double dicer mutant strain exhibited significantly slower growth. Furthermore, the Δdcl-1/dcl-2 double mutant, which was slow growing without virus infection, exhibited much more severe debilitation following virus infections including phenotypic changes such as slower growth, reduced pigmentation, and delayed sclerotial formation. These phenotypic changes were absent in the single mutants, Δdcl-1 and Δdcl-2. Complementation of a single dicer in the double disruption mutant reversed viral susceptibility to the wild-type state. Virus-derived small RNAs were accumulated from virus-infected wild-type strains with strand bias towards the negative sense. The findings of these studies indicate that S. sclerotiorum has robust RNA silencing mechanisms that process both DNA and RNA mycoviruses and that, when both dicers are silenced, invasive nucleic acids can greatly debilitate the virulence of this fungus.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gene Discovery in Acute Myeloid Leukaemia: somatic and germline mutations.</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/leo_et_al/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Aug 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/leo_et_al/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Location: Melbourne, Australia&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Event: International Congress of Immunology, 2016&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;
:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gene and mutation discovery in cancers is typically performed by sequencing somatic and germline samples from the same individuals and subtracting germline mutations.
However, in biobanked acute myeloid leukaemia (AML) samples, matched germline DNA is
frequently unavailable. When germline samples a
re available, sequencing both germline and
somatic samples for each patient significantly increases costs. This study explores whether it is possible to utilise unrelated germline controls to identify ocogenic drivers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methods&lt;/strong&gt;
:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whole exome sequencing was performed on somatic samples from 188 adults and children with AML (n=144 and n=44 respectively) and 429 control germline samples. The discovery process includes a rigorous statistical genetics approach whereby the AML cases and controls are age and ethnically matched. Residual population stratification is controlled by appropriate covariates. Burden tests are performed to detect mutations enriched in somatic samples compared to the unrelated germline controls. Statistical significance is determined by Q-Q plots against the null hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt;
:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Burden tests that included damaging protein coding mutations identified genes
previously described with recurrent mutations in AML (e.g.
NPM1, DNMT3A, IDH2, NRAS,
RUNX1, FLT3, IDH1, TET2, ASXL1
) thus validating th
is bioinformatics approach.
Furthermore, this methodology resulted in the detection of several additional novel genes not previously identified in AML.
These mutations are currently undergoing conventional validation by Sanger sequencing, as well as bioinformatic validation using whole genome sequencing data from 128 of the same AML samples sequenced using the Complete Genomics platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Discussion&lt;/strong&gt;
:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We demonstrate that this methodology can:
1) Identify technical artefacts from sequencing and alignment.
2) Enable statistical modelling of allele frequencies that can identify low frequency clones which are undetectable using standard genotyping approaches.
3) Provide a purely statistical approach to gene discovery, agnostic to mutation type
(synonymous, coding, non-coding etc).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusions&lt;/strong&gt;
:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, we have performed whole exome and whole genome sequencing on the largest cohort of AML samples in Australia. Innovative bioinformatic analysis has detected all previously identified, somatically mutated AML genes and has discovered a number of potentially significant novel mutations. The functional and prognostic impact of these events and the subsequent functional investigations will be discussed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MEK inhibitor resistance in acute myeloid leukaemia</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/mek_brisbane_2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/mek_brisbane_2016/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Location: Peppers Noosa, Australia&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Event: New Direction in Leukaemia Research, 2016&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mutations of the RAS family of genes are frequent events in AML, occurring in 10% of children and 10-20% of adults.
NRASmutations promote proliferation through activation of the Ras/Raf/MEK/ERK signalling pathway. Several MEK
inhibitors have shown promising pre-clinical activity in AML, with a number of compounds currently in adult phase I/II
clinical trials, including AZD6244, GSK1120212 and AS703026. Given not all patients respond to MEK inhibitor
treatment we undertook a comprehensive preclinical evaluation of MEK inhibitors in AML and developed a clinically
relevant model of resistance.
The in vitroefficacy of 7 MEK inhibitors was determined using a diverse panel of 6 paediatric and 5 adult AML cell lines
(Table 1). All AML cell lines were sensitive to at least one MEK inhibitor with the exception of the Down syndrome
associated AML line, CMK, and the adult erythroblastic line, HEL, that showed overt resistance (IC50 &amp;gt;20μM) to MEK
inhibition (Table 1). In sensitive cell lines, the reduced proliferation was associated with apoptosis, as assessed by
Annexin V+ staining. To confirm mechanism of action, inhibition of MEK phosphorylation as well as the downstream
kinase, pERK, were assessed by immunoblotting. The level of basal MEK activation was variable across the cell line
panel and pMEK was increased upon exposure to active MEK inhibitors. In contrast, levels of pERK were reduced
suggesting that MEK inhibitors may disrupt the interaction of MEK with its downstream transducers rather than a direct
inhibition of MEK phosphorylation.
Molecular and clinical resistance to kinase inhibitors is well described for targets such as FLT3 and BCR-ABL1. Since
clinical responses to MEK inhibitors have been variable, we investigated the potential mechanisms of resistance to
MEK inhibitors in vitro. Long-term culture of THP-1 cells (MLL-rearranged, NRASmutated) with AZD6244 and
AS703026, resulted in high-level resistance. Importantly, cells displayed cross-resistance not only to these two
compounds but also a third MEK inhibitor, GSK1120212 (Table 2). Resistance was associated with reduced basal
pMEK expression. In order to establish the mechanism of resistance we performed comprehensive mutation and gene
expression analyses utilising whole-exome sequencing and RNAseq respectively. These data revealed a spectrum of
acquired molecular aberrations common to both resistant cell lines compared to the parental THP1 cells. Together,
these data indicate that whilst MEK inhibition is a promising strategy to treat AML, resistance to one MEK inhibitor may
lead to cross-resistance to other compounds targeting MEK.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sensitivity of Whole Exome Sequencing for the Detection of FLT3-ITD and NPM1 Mutations in Acute Myeloid Leukaemia</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/esh_2015_buddapest/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Sep 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/esh_2015_buddapest/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Location: Buddapest, Hungary&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Event: European School of Hematology (ESH), 2015&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whole exome sequencing (WES) can detect a high proportion of cancer causing genetic mutations, and therefore has the potential to replace targeted molecular assays and identify additional novel, patient-specific mutations. To test the ability of WES to detect variants of clinical consequence, we compared WES findings to results for FLT3-ITD and NPM1mut obtained by routine pathology testing (high-resolution fragment analysis (HRFA) and Matrix Assisted Laser Desorption/Ionization – Time of Flight Mass Spectrometry (MALDI-TOF) respectively), and to point mutation findings in DNMT3A, IDH1/2, JAK2, KRAS, NRAS and MPL, as determined by Sequenom, across a cohort of 188 AML samples from adults (n
= 144) and children (n = 44). All subjects provided written informed consent, and the study protocols had been approved by institutional research ethics committees. Median age at diagnosis was 51 years, (range 1-89) and median bone marrow blast percentage was 76% (range 8-100).
A discovery phase using 96 samples developed genotype algorithms and ascertained their sensitivity. NPM1mut were reliably detected using WES, with 100% (n=25 positive) concordance with MALDI-TOF. WES and Sequenom were 99.4% concordant over the selected gene panels (1594 measurements). The FLT3-ITD false negative rate initially exceeded 50%, leading us to optimize our discovery algorithms and develop a calibration curve which specified the sequence coverage needed over the FLT3-ITD region to reliably genotype at any allelic ratio (AR). We demonstrate that our algorithms can reliably detect FLT3-ITD with AR &amp;gt; 0.05 using exome capture with less than 100x coverage over the FLT3-ITD region.
Additionally, we tested the algorithms over another 900 germline controls with no false positive measurements.
In a validation phase using 78 samples, all NPM1mut samples (n=20 positive) were detected, including an additional NPM1mut (type A) initially missed using MALDI-TOF. Concordance with Sequenom again exceeded 99.5% (comparable to the error rate expected in this Sequenom panel). For FLT3-ITD, &lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;21&lt;/sub&gt; HRFA-positive samples were detected with all 3 false-negatives falling outside the predicted sensitivity threshold; two samples with AR &amp;lt;0.01 (which would require sequencing coverage of 500x for detection) and one with AR = 0.4 but with a sequence coverage of only 38x over the FLT3-ITD.
In conclusion, we have performed WES on one of the largest cohorts of adult and paediatric AML described to date and demonstrate that clinically relevant mutations, including FLT3-ITD and NPM1mut, can be simultaneously detected with a single exome capture platform with accuracy similar to or better than current methods.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transcriptome analysis of western corn rootworm larvae and eggs</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/wcr_neupane/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/wcr_neupane/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Location: Chicago, USA&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Event: The International Working Group on Ostrinia and other Maize Pests (IWGO), 2014&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The     western     corn     rootworm,     Diabrotica     virgifera     virgifera(Coloeptera: Chrysomelidae), is one of the most devastating pests of corn causing nearly a billion dollars  of  financial  loss  both  in  terms  of  yield  loss  and  treatment  costs.  Although  Coleoptera  is  the  most  diverse  order  of  insects  comprising  more  than  400,000  species,  only  a  few  coleopteran  genomes  and  transcriptomes  (e.g.,  from  &lt;em&gt;Tribolium castaneum&lt;/em&gt;  and &lt;em&gt;Dendroctonus  ponderosae&lt;/em&gt;)  have  been  published  to  date.  The  genome size of haploid D. v.   virgifera is estimated to be ~2.58 GB, one of the largest among beetle species. Its complete genome sequence is currently in the draft stage. In this study, in order to identify the gene sets expressed in their larval stages (when the  most  damage  to  corn  is  caused)  and  to  contribute  to  improving  the  genome  assembly,  we  have  sequenced  and  assembled  transcriptomes  from  egg,  neonate,  and third-instar larval stages of D. v. virgifera using next-generation technologies. In total  ~700  gigabases  were  sequenced.  De  novo  transcriptome  assembly  was  performed using four different short read assemblers for individual  and  pooled  sets  of  reads.  Hybrid  assembly  using  both  Illumina  and  454  reads  was  also  performed.  After  examining  the  assembly  quality  based  on  contig  length  and  annotation  effectiveness  with  similarity  search,  we  chose  the  Trinity  assembly  from  the  pooled dataset  including  163,871  contigs  (the  average  length:  914  bp)  as  the  most  inclusive.  We  identified  and  annotated  genes  encoding  chemoreceptors,  gamma-aminobutyric  acid  (GABA)  type  A  receptor,  and  glycoside  hydrolase  families.  Compared  to  the  sequences  found  in  the  draft  genome,  we  observed  variations  in  sequences  as  well  as  in  the  number  of  introns.  We  also  examined  conservation  of  gene   structures   in   chemoreceptors   from   closely   related   insect   lineages.   Our   transcriptome sequences can contribute toward improved quality of the &lt;em&gt;D&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;v&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;virgiferagenome&lt;/em&gt; assembly and annotations.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genetic diversity and population structure of sickleweed(Falcaria vulgaris; Apiaceae) in the upper Midwest USA</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/piya_et_al_biological_invasions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2014 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/piya_et_al_biological_invasions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sickleweed (Falcaria vulgaris), an intro-duced species native to Europe and Asia, grows as anaggressive weed in some areas of the upper Midwest inthe United States. We are reporting genetic diversityand  population  structure  of  sickleweed  populationsusing microsatellite markers and nuclear and chloro-plast   DNA   sequences.   Populations   showed   highgenetic  differentiation  but  did  not  show  significantgeographic  structure,  suggesting  random  establish-ment of different genotypes at different sites was likelydue to human mediated multiple introductions. Threegenetic  clusters  revealed  by  microsatellite  data  andpresence of six chlorotypes supported our hypothesisof multiple introductions. Chloroplast DNA sequencedata  revealed  six  chlorotypes  nested  into  two  mainlineages   suggesting   at   least   two   introductions   ofsickleweed  in  the  upper  Midwest.  Some  individualsexhibited more than two alleles at several microsatel-lite  loci suggesting  occurrence  of polyploidy, whichcould be a post-introduction development to mitigatethe  inbreeding  effects.  High  genetic  variation  in  theintroduced range attributable to multiple introductionsand  polyploidy  may  be  inducing  the  evolution  ofinvasiveness  in  sickleweed.  Results  of  this  studyprovide valuable insights into the evolution of sickle-weed and baseline data for designing proper manage-ment practices for controlling sickleweed in the UnitedStates.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolutionary history of mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) genes in Lotus, Medicago, and Phaseolus</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/mapk_legume/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2013 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/mapk_legume/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mitogen-Activated Protein Kinase (MAPK) genes encode proteins that mediate various signaling pathways associated with biotic and abiotic stress responses in eukaryotes. The MAPK genes form a 3-tier signal transduction cascade between cellular stimuli and physiological responses. Recent identification of soybean MAPKs and availability of genome sequences from other legume species allowed us to identify their MAPK genes. The main objectives of this study were to identify MAPKs in 3 legume species, Lotus japonicus, Medicago truncatula, and Phaseolus vulgaris, and to assess their phylogenetic relationships. We used approaches in comparative genomics for MAPK gene identification and named the newly identified genes following Arabidopsis MAPK nomenclature model. We identified 19, 18, and 15 MAPKs and 7, 4, and 9 MAPKKs in the genome of Lotus japonicus, Medicago truncatula, and Phaseolus vulgaris, respectively. Within clade placement of MAPKs and MAPKKs in the 3 legume species were consistent with those in soybean and Arabidopsis. Among 5 clades of MAPKs, 4 founder clades were consistent to MAPKs of other plant species and orthologs of MAPK genes in the fifth clade-&amp;ldquo;Clade E&amp;rdquo; were consistent with those in soybean. Our results also indicated that some gene duplication events might have occurred prior to eudicot-monocot divergence. Highly diversified MAPKs in soybean relative to those in 3 other legume species are attributable to the polyploidization events in soybean. The identification of the MAPK genes in the legume species is important for the legume crop improvement; and evolutionary relationships and functional divergence of these gene members provide insights into plant genome evolution.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identification, Nomenclature, and Evolutionary Relationships of Mitogen-Activated Protein Kinase (MAPK) Genes in Soybean</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/mapk_soybean/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Sep 2013 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/mapk_soybean/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) genes in eukaryotes regulate various developmental and physiological processes
including those associated with biotic and abiotic stresses. Although MAPKs in some plant species including Arabidopsis have been
identified, they are yet to be identified in soybean. Major objectives of this study were to identify GmMAPKs, assess their evolutionary relationships, and analyze their functional divergence. We identified a total of 38 MAPKs, eleven MAPKKs, and 150 MAPKKKs in
soybean. Within the GmMAPK family, we also identified a new clade of six genes: four genes with TEY and two genes with TQY motifs
requiring further investigation into possible legume-specific functions. The results indicated the expansion of the GmMAPK families
attributable to the ancestral polyploidy events followed by chromosomal rearrangements. The GmMAPK and GmMAPKKK families
were substantially larger than those in other plant species. The duplicated GmMAPK members presented complex evolutionary relationships and functional divergence when compared to their counterparts in Arabidopsis. We also highlighted existing nomenclatural issues,
stressing the need for nomenclatural consistency. GmMAPK identification is vital to soybean crop improvement, and novel insights into
the evolutionary relationships will enhance our understanding about plant genome evolution.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identification of Mitogen Activated Protein Kinase Family Members in Soybean</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/bsa_neupane/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jul 2012 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/bsa_neupane/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Location: Ohio, USA&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Event: Botanical Society of America Conference, 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mitogen Activated Protein Kinases (MAPKs) are serine/threonine specific kinases that are induced by various extracellular and intracellular stimuli, and are involved in signaling pathways in all eukaryotes. In plants, MAPKs are known to regulate various signal transduction pathways including those associated with biotic and abiotic stresses. The MAPK gene members belong to three functionally linked gene families called MAPKs, MAPKKs (MAPK Kinases) and MAPKKKs (MAPKK Kinases). Although, MAPKs of model plants such as &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Oryza&lt;/em&gt; have been identified and characterized, these genes in soybean (&lt;em&gt;Glycine max&lt;/em&gt;) are yet to be identified. In this study, we used approaches in comparative genomics and bioinformatics for the genome-wide identification of MAPKs, MAPKKs and MAPKKKs in soybean. &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/em&gt; reference sequences were used in protein BLAST to search the putative MAPKs of soybean from publicly available databases. In our in-silico analysis, the redundant sequences were removed to perform unbiased and rigorous phylogenetic analyses. We verified the presence of unique conserved domains and active sites in each putative MAPK gene member manually and by using Geneious and Pfam programs. From our three different confirmatory analyses, we identified 38 MAP Kinases, 11 MAPK Kinases and 115 MAPKK Kinases in soybean. &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/em&gt; nomenclature model was followed to assign numeric subscript to MAPK sequences grouped with &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/em&gt; sequences in phylogenetic tree. Lack of effective code of nomenclature lead us to a conundrum, which will be discussed in the meeting. Universal codes of gene nomenclature are crucial for understanding various signaling pathways. Therefore, an effective code of gene nomenclature is warranted. The results from this study will help us characterize soybean MAP Kinases paving avenue for the functional analyses of different cellular and physiological pathways in the order these genes function.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Population Genetics of *Falcaria vulgaris* (Sickleweed) in North America</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/piya_bsa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jul 2012 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/piya_bsa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Location: Ohio, USA&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Event: Botanical Society of America Conference, 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction history and spread of Falcaria vulgaris Bernh. (Apiaceae) in the United States based on herbarium records</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/piya_sd_academy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Apr 2012 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/piya_sd_academy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Location: Vermillion, SD, USA&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Event: South Dakota Academy of Science, 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Nomenclatural Conundrum: Applying Existing Nomenclature to the Identification of Soybean (*Glycine max*) MAP Kinase Genes</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/neupane_aspb/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Mar 2012 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/neupane_aspb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Location: Nebraska, USA&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Event: American Society of Plant Biologists, Midwestern Sectional Society, 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inferring Introduction History and Spread of Falcaria vulgaris Bernh.(Apiaceae) in the United States Based on Herbarium Records</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/piya_et_al_proceedings_sd/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2012 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/piya_et_al_proceedings_sd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Herbarium records were studied to infer the introduction history and spread of the exotic Eurasian sickleweed (Falcaria vulgaris Bernh.) in the United States. The spread of the plant was reconstructed using the location of early collections as the possible sites of primary introduction, and the location of subsequent collections as potential pathways along which this species spread. Herbarium records indicate that sickleweed was first introduced no later than 1922, and independent introduction of this plant took place in the East Coast and in the Midwest of the United States. The species has spread to 37 counties of 15 states of the United States. No recent sickleweed record has been reported for the last 17 years in the US except Iowa, Nebraska and South Dakota. The plant has been characterized as an aggressive weed by experts in the latter two states, where it is already well established and has infested the Fort Pierre National Grassland and Buffalo Gap National Grassland in South Dakota, and is reported from several sites along Nebraska roadsides. It is essential to verify the existence of sickleweed in the areas from where the herbarium specimens were previously collected to help identify the areas at risk. Control strategies need to be implemented and policy should be developed to establish the participation of public lands managers, transportation departments and private land-owners to control and manage this species before it becomes a more widespread invader.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Anticancer Activity of Novel Ionic Triorganotin Derivatives against MDA-MB 231 Breast Cancer Cells</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/hbcu_neupane/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2009 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/hbcu_neupane/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Location: Washington DC, USA&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Event: HBCU-UP National Research Conference, 2009&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of this project was to study the responses of antibodies
against four influenza A viruses; PR8, RV6, Swine and J1. RV6,
Swine and J1 differ from PR8 by 1 amino acid (99.9% similarity),
20 amino acids, and more than 100 amino acids, respectively.
Despite several attempts of early diagnosis and chemotherapy,
breast cancer is one of the leading causes of cancer deaths in
United States claiming almost 40610 lives per year. Breast cancer
is more common in white women than in African American women
but the survival rate for 5 years for African American women is
comparatively less which is 77% than 90 % for white women.
Higher concentration of estrogen secretion has also been
associated with the risk factors of breast cancer.
These viruses resemble the different viruses that circulate in
people and that can have varying numbers of amino acid
differences, and we wanted to examine how these difference
affect the ability of antibodies to bind to different viruses using
different techniques. ELISA (Enzyme Linked Immunosorbent
Assay) was used to determine whether a particular antibody is
present in a blood sample and ELISPOT (ELISPOT-Enzyme-linked
Immunospot assay) was used for enumeration of B cells secreting
specific antibody.
In recent studies, metal-based anticancer drugs are found to be
very effective in the death of cancer cells proving it as a very
useful cancer chemotherapeutic. In this study we have
synthesized ionic triorganotin compounds with increased solubility
due to their partially ionic characteristic and tested their anticancer activity using MDA-MB 231 breast cancer cells.
Methods: Three compounds (1) Triphenyltin Hydroxide&lt;a href=&#34;2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;parent
compound&lt;/a&gt; CA11 and (3) CA 32 derivatives were tested.
MDA-MB 231 cells were plated in 96-wellplate and treated with
varying concentration (1ng to 100ug) of various triorganotin
derivatives for 24, 48 and 72 hours. A combination of trypan blue
dye exclusion and WST-1 cell proliferation reagent was used to&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
