<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Chezaray Anjorin | Achal Neupane</title>
    <link>/achalneupane.github.io/authors/chezaray-anjorin/</link>
      <atom:link href="/achalneupane.github.io/authors/chezaray-anjorin/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Chezaray Anjorin</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2019</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2009 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/achalneupane.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Chezaray Anjorin</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/authors/chezaray-anjorin/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Anticancer Activity of Novel Ionic Triorganotin Derivatives against MDA-MB 231 Breast Cancer Cells</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/hbcu_neupane/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2009 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/hbcu_neupane/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of this project was to study the responses of antibodies
against four influenza A viruses; PR8, RV6, Swine and J1. RV6,
Swine and J1 differ from PR8 by 1 amino acid (99.9% similarity),
20 amino acids, and more than 100 amino acids, respectively.
Despite several attempts of early diagnosis and chemotherapy,
breast cancer is one of the leading causes of cancer deaths in
United States claiming almost 40610 lives per year. Breast cancer
is more common in white women than in African American women
but the survival rate for 5 years for African American women is
comparatively less which is 77% than 90 % for white women.
Higher concentration of estrogen secretion has also been
associated with the risk factors of breast cancer.
These viruses resemble the different viruses that circulate in
people and that can have varying numbers of amino acid
differences, and we wanted to examine how these difference
affect the ability of antibodies to bind to different viruses using
different techniques. ELISA (Enzyme Linked Immunosorbent
Assay) was used to determine whether a particular antibody is
present in a blood sample and ELISPOT (ELISPOT-Enzyme-linked
Immunospot assay) was used for enumeration of B cells secreting
specific antibody.
In recent studies, metal-based anticancer drugs are found to be
very effective in the death of cancer cells proving it as a very
useful cancer chemotherapeutic. In this study we have
synthesized ionic triorganotin compounds with increased solubility
due to their partially ionic characteristic and tested their anticancer activity using MDA-MB 231 breast cancer cells.
Methods: Three compounds (1) Triphenyltin Hydroxide&lt;a href=&#34;2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;parent
compound&lt;/a&gt; CA11 and (3) CA 32 derivatives were tested.
MDA-MB 231 cells were plated in 96-wellplate and treated with
varying concentration (1ng to 100ug) of various triorganotin
derivatives for 24, 48 and 72 hours. A combination of trypan blue
dye exclusion and WST-1 cell proliferation reagent was used to&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
