<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Felicity Newell | Achal Neupane</title>
    <link>/achalneupane.github.io/authors/felicity-newell/</link>
      <atom:link href="/achalneupane.github.io/authors/felicity-newell/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Felicity Newell</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2019</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Aug 2016 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/achalneupane.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Felicity Newell</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/authors/felicity-newell/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gene Discovery in Acute Myeloid Leukaemia: somatic and germline mutations.</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/leo_et_al/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Aug 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/leo_et_al/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;
:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gene and mutation discovery in cancers is typically performed by sequencing somatic and germline samples from the same individuals and subtracting germline mutations.
However, in biobanked acute myeloid leukaemia (AML) samples, matched germline DNA is
frequently unavailable. When germline samples are available, sequencing both germline and somatic samples for each patient significantly increases costs. This study explores whether it is possible to utilise unrelated germline controls to identify ocogenic drivers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methods&lt;/strong&gt;
:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whole exome sequencing was performed on somatic samples from 188 adults and children with AML (n=144 and n=44 respectively) and 429 control germline samples. The discovery process includes a rigorous statistical genetics approach whereby the AML cases and controls are age and ethnically matched. Residual population stratification is controlled by appropriate covariates. Burden tests are performed to detect mutations enriched in somatic samples compared to the unrelated germline controls. Statistical significance is determined by Q-Q plots against the null hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt;
:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Burden tests that included damaging protein coding mutations identified genes
previously described with recurrent mutations in AML (e.g.
NPM1, DNMT3A, IDH2, NRAS, RUNX1, FLT3, IDH1, TET2, ASXL1) thus validating this bioinformatics approach.
Furthermore, this methodology resulted in the detection of several additional novel genes not previously identified in AML.
These mutations are currently undergoing conventional validation by Sanger sequencing, as well as bioinformatic validation using whole genome sequencing data from 128 of the same AML samples sequenced using the Complete Genomics platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Discussion&lt;/strong&gt;
:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We demonstrate that this methodology can:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify technical artefacts from sequencing and alignment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enable statistical modelling of allele frequencies that can identify low frequency clones which are undetectable using standard genotyping approaches.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide a purely statistical approach to gene discovery, agnostic to mutation type
(synonymous, coding, non-coding etc).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusions&lt;/strong&gt;
:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, we have performed whole exome and whole genome sequencing on the largest cohort of AML samples in Australia. Innovative bioinformatic analysis has detected all previously identified, somatically mutated AML genes and has discovered a number of potentially significant novel mutations. The functional and prognostic impact of these events and the subsequent functional investigations will be discussed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sensitivity of Whole Exome Sequencing for the Detection of FLT3-ITD and NPM1 Mutations in Acute Myeloid Leukaemia</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/esh_2015_buddapest/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Sep 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/talk/esh_2015_buddapest/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whole exome sequencing (WES) can detect a high proportion of cancer causing genetic mutations, and therefore has the potential to replace targeted molecular assays and identify additional novel, patient-specific mutations. To test the ability of WES to detect variants of clinical consequence, we compared WES findings to results for FLT3-ITD and NPM1mut obtained by routine pathology testing (high-resolution fragment analysis (HRFA) and Matrix Assisted Laser Desorption/Ionization – Time of Flight Mass Spectrometry (MALDI-TOF) respectively), and to point mutation findings in DNMT3A, IDH1/2, JAK2, KRAS, NRAS and MPL, as determined by Sequenom, across a cohort of 188 AML samples from adults (n
= 144) and children (n = 44). All subjects provided written informed consent, and the study protocols had been approved by institutional research ethics committees. Median age at diagnosis was 51 years, (range 1-89) and median bone marrow blast percentage was 76% (range 8-100).
A discovery phase using 96 samples developed genotype algorithms and ascertained their sensitivity. NPM1mut were reliably detected using WES, with 100% (n=25 positive) concordance with MALDI-TOF. WES and Sequenom were 99.4% concordant over the selected gene panels (1594 measurements). The FLT3-ITD false negative rate initially exceeded 50%, leading us to optimize our discovery algorithms and develop a calibration curve which specified the sequence coverage needed over the FLT3-ITD region to reliably genotype at any allelic ratio (AR). We demonstrate that our algorithms can reliably detect FLT3-ITD with AR &amp;gt; 0.05 using exome capture with less than 100x coverage over the FLT3-ITD region.
Additionally, we tested the algorithms over another 900 germline controls with no false positive measurements.
In a validation phase using 78 samples, all NPM1mut samples (n=20 positive) were detected, including an additional NPM1mut (type A) initially missed using MALDI-TOF. Concordance with Sequenom again exceeded 99.5% (comparable to the error rate expected in this Sequenom panel). For FLT3-ITD, 18/21 HRFA-positive samples were detected with all 3 false-negatives falling outside the predicted sensitivity threshold; two samples with AR &amp;lt;0.01 (which would require sequencing coverage of 500x for detection) and one with AR = 0.4 but with a sequence coverage of only 38x over the FLT3-ITD.
In conclusion, we have performed WES on one of the largest cohorts of adult and paediatric AML described to date and demonstrate that clinically relevant mutations, including FLT3-ITD and NPM1mut, can be simultaneously detected with a single exome capture platform with accuracy similar to or better than current methods.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
