<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Publications | Achal Neupane</title>
    <link>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/</link>
      <atom:link href="/achalneupane.github.io/publication/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Publications</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2019</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2019 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/achalneupane.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roles of argonautes  and dicers on Sclerotinia sclerotiorum antiviral RNA silencing</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/neupane_etal_2019_frontiers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2019 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/neupane_etal_2019_frontiers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RNA silencing or RNA interference (RNAi) is an essential mechanism in animals, fungi, and plants that functions in gene regulation and defense against foreign nucleic acids. In fungi, RNA silencing has been shown to function primarily in defense against invasive nucleic acids. We previously determined that mycoviruses are triggers and targets of RNA silencing in Sclerotinia sclerotiorum. However, recent progresses in RNAi or dsRNA-based pest control requires more detailed characterization of the RNA silencing pathways in S. sclerotiorum to investigate the utility of dsRNA-based strategy for white mold control. This study elucidates the roles of argonaute enzymes, agl-2 and agl-4, in small RNA metabolism in S. sclerotiorum. Gene disruption mutants of agl-2 and agl-4 were compared for changes in phenotype, virulence, viral susceptibility, and small RNA profiles. The Δagl-2 mutant but not the Δagl-4 mutant had significantly slower growth and virulence prior to virus infection. Similarly, the Δagl-2 mutant but not the Δagl-4 mutant, showed greater debilitation under virus infection compared to uninfected strains. The responses were confirmed in complementation studies and revealed the antiviral role of agl-2. Gene disruption mutants of agl-2, agl-4, Dicer-like (dcl)-1, and dcl-2 did not change the stability of the most abundant endogenous small RNAs, which suggests the existence of alternative enzymes/pathways for small RNA biogenesis in S. sclerotiorum. Furthermore, in vitro synthesized dsRNA targeting agl-2 showed a significantly reduced average lesion diameter (P &amp;lt; 0.05) on canola leaves with agl-2 down-regulated compared to controls. This is the first report describing the effectiveness of RNA pesticides targeting S. sclerotiorum RNA silencing pathway for the control of the economically important pathogen.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identification and Characterization of Mitogen-Activated Protein Kinase (MAPK) Genes in Sunflower (Helianthus annuus L.)</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/surendra_et_al_2019_plants/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jan 2019 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/surendra_et_al_2019_plants/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mitogen-Activated Protein Kinase (MAPK) genes encode proteins that regulate biotic and abiotic stresses in plants through signaling cascades comprised of three major subfamilies: MAP Kinase (MPK), MAPK Kinase (MKK), and MAPKK Kinase (MKKK). The main objectives of this research were to conduct genome-wide identification of MAPK genes in Helianthus annuus and examine functional divergence of these genes in relation to those in nine other plant species (Amborella trichopoda, Aquilegia coerulea, Arabidopsis thaliana, Daucus carota, Glycine max, Oryza sativa, Solanum lycopersicum, Sphagnum fallax, and Vitis vinifera), representing diverse taxonomic groups of the Plant Kingdom. A Hidden Markov Model (HMM) profile of the MAPK genes utilized reference sequences from A. thaliana and G. max, yielding a total of 96 MPKs and 37 MKKs in the genomes of A. trichopoda, A. coerulea, C. reinhardtii, D. carota, H. annuus, S. lycopersicum, and S. fallax. Among them, 28 MPKs and eight MKKs were confirmed in H. annuus. Phylogenetic analyses revealed four clades within each subfamily. Transcriptomic analyses showed that at least 19 HaMPK and seven HaMKK genes were induced in response to salicylic acid (SA), sodium chloride (NaCl), and polyethylene glycol (Peg) in leaves and roots. Of the seven published sunflower microRNAs, five microRNA families are involved in targeting eight MPKs. Additionally, we discussed the need for using MAP Kinase nomenclature guidelines across plant species. Our identification and characterization of MAP Kinase genes would have implications in sunflower crop improvement, and in advancing our knowledge of the diversity and evolution of MAPK genes in the Plant Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Metatranscriptomic analysis and in silico approach identified mycoviruses in the arbuscular mycorrhizal fungus Rhizophagus spp.</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/neupane_etal_viruses_2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2018 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/neupane_etal_viruses_2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi (AMF), including Rhizophagus spp., can play important roles in nutrient cycling of the rhizosphere. However, the effect of virus infection on AMF’s role in nutrient cycling cannot be determined without first knowing the diversity of the mycoviruses in AMF. Therefore, in this study, we sequenced the R. irregularis isolate-09 due to its previously demonstrated high efficiency in increasing the N/P uptake of the plant. We identified one novel mitovirus contig of 3685 bp, further confirmed by reverse transcription-PCR. Also, publicly available Rhizophagus spp. RNA-Seq data were analyzed to recover five partial virus sequences from family Narnaviridae, among which four were from R. diaphanum MUCL-43196 and one was from R. irregularis strain-C2 that was similar to members of the Mitovirus genus. These contigs coded genomes larger than the regular mitoviruses infecting pathogenic fungi and can be translated by either a mitochondrial translation code or a cytoplasmic translation code, which was also reported in previously found mitoviruses infecting mycorrhizae. The five newly identified virus sequences are comprised of functionally conserved RdRp motifs and formed two separate subclades with mitoviruses infecting Gigaspora margarita and Rhizophagus clarus, further supporting virus-host co-evolution theory. This study expands our understanding of virus diversity. Even though AMF is notably hard to investigate due to its biotrophic nature, this study demonstrates the utility of whole root metatranscriptome.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transcriptional and small RNA responses of the white mold fungus Sclerotinia sclerotiorum to infection by a virulence-attenuating hypovirus</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/marzano_etal_viruses_2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Dec 2018 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/marzano_etal_viruses_2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mycoviruses belonging to the family Hypoviridae cause persistent infection of many different host fungi. We previously determined that the white mold fungus, Sclerotinia sclerotiorum, infected with Sclerotinia sclerotiorum hypovirus 2-L (SsHV2-L) exhibits reduced virulence, delayed/reduced sclerotial formation, and enhanced production of aerial mycelia. To gain better insight into the cellular basis for these changes, we characterized changes in mRNA and small RNA (sRNA) accumulation in S. sclerotiorum to infection by SsHV2-L. A total of 958 mRNAs and 835 sRNA-producing loci were altered after infection by SsHV2-L, among which &amp;gt;100 mRNAs were predicted to encode proteins involved in the metabolism and trafficking of carbohydrates and lipids. Both S. sclerotiorum endogenous and virus-derived sRNAs were predominantly 22 nt in length suggesting one dicer-like enzyme cleaves both. Novel classes of endogenous small RNAs were predicted, including phasiRNAs and tRNA-derived small RNAs. Moreover, S. sclerotiorum phasiRNAs, which were derived from noncoding RNAs and have the potential to regulate mRNA abundance in trans, showed differential accumulation due to virus infection. tRNA fragments did not accumulate differentially after hypovirus infection. Hence, in-depth analysis showed that infection of S. sclerotiorum by a hypovirulence-inducing hypovirus produced selective, large-scale reprogramming of mRNA and sRNA production.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genome-Wide Identification of NBS-Encoding Resistance Genes in Sunflower (Helianthus annuus L.)</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/surendra_et_al_2018_july_genes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jun 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/surendra_et_al_2018_july_genes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nucleotide Binding Site-Leucine-Rich Repeat (NBS-LRR) genes encode disease resistance proteins involved in plants&amp;rsquo; defense against their pathogens. Although sunflower is affected by many diseases, only a few molecular details have been uncovered regarding pathogenesis and resistance mechanisms. Recent availability of sunflower whole genome sequences in publicly accessible databases allowed us to accomplish a genome-wide identification of Toll-interleukin-1 receptor-like Nucleotide-binding site Leucine-rich repeat (TNL), Coiled Coil (CC)-NBS-LRR (CNL), Resistance to powdery mildew 8 (RPW8)-NBS-LRR (RNL) and NBS-LRR (NL) protein encoding genes. Hidden Markov Model (HMM) profiling of 52,243 putative protein sequences from sunflower resulted in 352 NBS-encoding genes, among which 100 genes belong to CNL group including 64 genes with RX_CC like domain, 77 to TNL, 13 to RNL, and 162 belong to NL group. We also identified signal peptides and nuclear localization signals present in the identified genes and their homologs. We found that NBS genes were located on all chromosomes and formed 75 gene clusters, one-third of which were located on chromosome 13. Phylogenetic analyses between sunflower and Arabidopsis NBS genes revealed a clade-specific nesting pattern in CNLs, with RNLs nested in the CNL-A clade, and species-specific nesting pattern for TNLs. Surprisingly, we found a moderate bootstrap support (BS = 50%) for CNL-A clade being nested within TNL clade making both the CNL and TNL clades paraphyletic. Arabidopsis and sunflower showed 87 syntenic blocks with 1049 high synteny hits between chromosome 5 of Arabidopsis and chromosome 6 of sunflower. Expression data revealed functional divergence of the NBS genes with basal level tissue-specific expression. This study represents the first genome-wide identification of NBS genes in sunflower paving avenues for functional characterization and potential crop improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mycoviruses as Triggers and Targets of RNA Silencing in White Mold Fungus Sclerotinia sclerotiorum</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/mochama_et_al/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Apr 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/mochama_et_al/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study aimed to demonstrate the existence of antiviral RNA silencing mechanisms in Sclerotinia sclerotiorum by infecting wild-type and RNA-silencing-deficient strains of the fungus with an RNA virus and a DNA virus. Key silencing-related genes were disrupted to dissect the RNA silencing pathway. Specifically, dicer genes (dcl-1, dcl-2, and both dcl-1/dcl-2) were displaced by selective marker(s). Disruption mutants were then compared for changes in phenotype, virulence, and susceptibility to virus infections. Wild-type and mutant strains were transfected with a single-stranded RNA virus, SsHV2-L, and copies of a single-stranded DNA mycovirus, SsHADV-1, as a synthetic virus constructed in this study. Disruption of dcl-1 or dcl-2 resulted in no changes in phenotype compared to wild-type S. sclerotiorum; however, the double dicer mutant strain exhibited significantly slower growth. Furthermore, the Δdcl-1/dcl-2 double mutant, which was slow growing without virus infection, exhibited much more severe debilitation following virus infections including phenotypic changes such as slower growth, reduced pigmentation, and delayed sclerotial formation. These phenotypic changes were absent in the single mutants, Δdcl-1 and Δdcl-2. Complementation of a single dicer in the double disruption mutant reversed viral susceptibility to the wild-type state. Virus-derived small RNAs were accumulated from virus-infected wild-type strains with strand bias towards the negative sense. The findings of these studies indicate that S. sclerotiorum has robust RNA silencing mechanisms that process both DNA and RNA mycoviruses and that, when both dicers are silenced, invasive nucleic acids can greatly debilitate the virulence of this fungus.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genetic diversity and population structure of sickleweed(Falcaria vulgaris; Apiaceae) in the upper Midwest USA</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/piya_et_al_biological_invasions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2014 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/piya_et_al_biological_invasions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sickleweed (Falcaria vulgaris), an intro-duced species native to Europe and Asia, grows as anaggressive weed in some areas of the upper Midwest inthe United States. We are reporting genetic diversityand  population  structure  of  sickleweed  populationsusing microsatellite markers and nuclear and chloro-plast   DNA   sequences.   Populations   showed   highgenetic  differentiation  but  did  not  show  significantgeographic  structure,  suggesting  random  establish-ment of different genotypes at different sites was likelydue to human mediated multiple introductions. Threegenetic  clusters  revealed  by  microsatellite  data  andpresence of six chlorotypes supported our hypothesisof multiple introductions. Chloroplast DNA sequencedata  revealed  six  chlorotypes  nested  into  two  mainlineages   suggesting   at   least   two   introductions   ofsickleweed  in  the  upper  Midwest.  Some  individualsexhibited more than two alleles at several microsatel-lite  loci suggesting  occurrence  of polyploidy, whichcould be a post-introduction development to mitigatethe  inbreeding  effects.  High  genetic  variation  in  theintroduced range attributable to multiple introductionsand  polyploidy  may  be  inducing  the  evolution  ofinvasiveness  in  sickleweed.  Results  of  this  studyprovide valuable insights into the evolution of sickle-weed and baseline data for designing proper manage-ment practices for controlling sickleweed in the UnitedStates.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolutionary history of mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) genes in Lotus, Medicago, and Phaseolus</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/mapk_legume/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2013 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/mapk_legume/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mitogen-Activated Protein Kinase (MAPK) genes encode proteins that mediate various signaling pathways associated with biotic and abiotic stress responses in eukaryotes. The MAPK genes form a 3-tier signal transduction cascade between cellular stimuli and physiological responses. Recent identification of soybean MAPKs and availability of genome sequences from other legume species allowed us to identify their MAPK genes. The main objectives of this study were to identify MAPKs in 3 legume species, Lotus japonicus, Medicago truncatula, and Phaseolus vulgaris, and to assess their phylogenetic relationships. We used approaches in comparative genomics for MAPK gene identification and named the newly identified genes following Arabidopsis MAPK nomenclature model. We identified 19, 18, and 15 MAPKs and 7, 4, and 9 MAPKKs in the genome of Lotus japonicus, Medicago truncatula, and Phaseolus vulgaris, respectively. Within clade placement of MAPKs and MAPKKs in the 3 legume species were consistent with those in soybean and Arabidopsis. Among 5 clades of MAPKs, 4 founder clades were consistent to MAPKs of other plant species and orthologs of MAPK genes in the fifth clade-&amp;ldquo;Clade E&amp;rdquo; were consistent with those in soybean. Our results also indicated that some gene duplication events might have occurred prior to eudicot-monocot divergence. Highly diversified MAPKs in soybean relative to those in 3 other legume species are attributable to the polyploidization events in soybean. The identification of the MAPK genes in the legume species is important for the legume crop improvement; and evolutionary relationships and functional divergence of these gene members provide insights into plant genome evolution.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identification, Nomenclature, and Evolutionary Relationships of Mitogen-Activated Protein Kinase (MAPK) Genes in Soybean</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/mapk_soybean/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Sep 2013 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/mapk_soybean/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) genes in eukaryotes regulate various developmental and physiological processes
including those associated with biotic and abiotic stresses. Although MAPKs in some plant species including Arabidopsis have been
identified, they are yet to be identified in soybean. Major objectives of this study were to identify GmMAPKs, assess their evolutionary relationships, and analyze their functional divergence. We identified a total of 38 MAPKs, eleven MAPKKs, and 150 MAPKKKs in
soybean. Within the GmMAPK family, we also identified a new clade of six genes: four genes with TEY and two genes with TQY motifs
requiring further investigation into possible legume-specific functions. The results indicated the expansion of the GmMAPK families
attributable to the ancestral polyploidy events followed by chromosomal rearrangements. The GmMAPK and GmMAPKKK families
were substantially larger than those in other plant species. The duplicated GmMAPK members presented complex evolutionary relationships and functional divergence when compared to their counterparts in Arabidopsis. We also highlighted existing nomenclatural issues,
stressing the need for nomenclatural consistency. GmMAPK identification is vital to soybean crop improvement, and novel insights into
the evolutionary relationships will enhance our understanding about plant genome evolution.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inferring Introduction History and Spread of Falcaria vulgaris Bernh.(Apiaceae) in the United States Based on Herbarium Records</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/piya_et_al_proceedings_sd/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2012 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/publication/piya_et_al_proceedings_sd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Herbarium records were studied to infer the introduction history and spread of the exotic Eurasian sickleweed (Falcaria vulgaris Bernh.) in the United States. The spread of the plant was reconstructed using the location of early collections as the possible sites of primary introduction, and the location of subsequent collections as potential pathways along which this species spread. Herbarium records indicate that sickleweed was first introduced no later than 1922, and independent introduction of this plant took place in the East Coast and in the Midwest of the United States. The species has spread to 37 counties of 15 states of the United States. No recent sickleweed record has been reported for the last 17 years in the US except Iowa, Nebraska and South Dakota. The plant has been characterized as an aggressive weed by experts in the latter two states, where it is already well established and has infested the Fort Pierre National Grassland and Buffalo Gap National Grassland in South Dakota, and is reported from several sites along Nebraska roadsides. It is essential to verify the existence of sickleweed in the areas from where the herbarium specimens were previously collected to help identify the areas at risk. Control strategies need to be implemented and policy should be developed to establish the participation of public lands managers, transportation departments and private land-owners to control and manage this species before it becomes a more widespread invader.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
