<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Achal Neupane</title>
    <link>/achalneupane.github.io/authors/admin/</link>
      <atom:link href="/achalneupane.github.io/authors/admin/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Achal Neupane</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2019</copyright>
    <image>
      <url>/achalneupane.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Achal Neupane</title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/authors/admin/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/achalneupane.github.io/authors/admin/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/achalneupane.github.io/authors/admin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been working on bioinformatics and statistical genetics focused projects. I have extensive experience in academic, clinical and industry collaborations with researchers in the US and Australia. I have gained key expertise in the analysis of large clinically focused datasets (mostly Cancer genomes). The goals of these research were to characterize and understand the genetic origin of disease and to translate these findings into clinical practice. In the past, I had analyzed a cohort of 150 clinically characterized acute myeloid leukemia (AML) sequenced with whole exome and whole genome sequencing, and a cohort of 900 control exomes and 600 whole genomes to validate and compare genotyping algorithms and sequencing technologies, and to perform gene discovery for both somatic and germline risk variants. For this, I used sophisticated statistical genetics algorithms that identify both protective and deleterious variants. I also used several variant calling methods to characterize germline, copy number and structural variants in AML. I also developed several algorithms (in R) for these studies, including to detect sample contamination, identity and ethnicity for quality control of Next Generation Sequencing (NGS) data. I also compared pathology, cytogenetic and Sequenom genotyping data to refine and calibrate these algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, I have studied the effects of hypovirulence-associated DNA virus 1(SsHADV-1) and Sclerotinia sclerotiorum hypovirus 2 Lactuca (SsHV2L) on white mold fungus pathogen &lt;em&gt;Sclerotinia sclerotiorum&lt;/em&gt; using small RNAseq and RNAseq data. Over the years, I have worked on human (Cancer), plants, insects, fungal and viral genome datasets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During my graduate studies, I had taken several &amp;ldquo;data-heavy&amp;rdquo; courses in Statistics and Computer science (besides Biological science) which fueled my interest in Data Science. I am interested in big data analysis, algorithm development, scientific computing, including analysis of biological (NGS)/non-biological datasets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Graduate level courses in Statistics and Computer science:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;pdf_html/CS_and_Stat.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;View&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
